Hey, welcome back.
欢迎回来
In the last video, I showed you these two matrices.
在上个视频中 我给出了这两个矩阵
And I mentioned that we can't calculate their matrix product.
并提到我们无法计算这两个矩阵的积
Now that you know how matrix multiplication works,
现在 当你知道矩阵乘法如何计算后
it's easier to see why we can't.
就很容易明白为何不能计算这两个矩阵的积了
Remember, we were finding a series
我们要计算
of dot products between the rows of the left matrix
一系列左侧矩阵的行与右侧矩阵的列
and the columns of the right.
之间的点积
And what do we need to find a dot product?
计算点积需要满足什么条件呢？
We need two vectors that are the same length.
两个向量长度必须相等
That means the rows of the first matrix
意味着第一个矩阵行的长度
need to be the same length as the columns
必须与第二个矩阵
of the second matrix.
列的长度相同
And what's the length of a row?
与行长度相等的是什么呢
Its number of columns.
是列的数量
And what's the length of a column?
与列长度相等的是什么呢
Its number of rows.
是行的数量
So that gives us a very important rule
这就得出了一个非常重要的
for matrix multiplication.
矩阵乘法规则
The number of columns in the left matrix
左侧矩阵的列数
must equal the number of rows in the matrix.
必须等于右侧矩阵的行数
You can see it easily when you write out their shape side
当你挨着写出它们的形状时
by side.
就很容易看出来了
Remember, we always specify the dimensions as rows by columns.
注意 我们始终将维度表示为行乘以列
So when you put them next to each other in the order you
所以当你将它们放在一起
plan to multiply them, the number
以便相乘时
of columns for the left matrix ends up here
左侧矩阵的列数
on the inside next to the number of rows for the right
就位于此处 在内测
matrix here.
并挨着右侧矩阵的行数
If you want to multiply two matrices,
如果想对两个矩阵相乘
these two inner dimensions need to be the same size.
这两个内部数大小必须相等
So we could find the product of this 2 by 3 matrix times this 3
所以我们可以计算这个 2 x 3 矩阵与
by 2 matrix, because these two 3's are the same.
这个 3 x 2 矩阵的积 因为这两个 3 相等
Or we could find the product of this 3 by 2 matrix and this 2
或者 我们可以计算这个 3 x 2 矩阵和
by 3 matrix, because these two 2's are the same.
这个 2 x 3 矩阵的积 因为这两个 2 相等
And it might take us a while, but we could even
我们甚至可以计算
find the product of a 10,000 by 300 matrix and 300
10,000 x 300 矩阵和 300 x 6,000 矩阵的积
by 6,000 matrix, because these two 300's are the same.
虽然要花点时间 因为这两个 300 相等
Just remember, when you look at their shapes side by side,
只需注意 当你紧挨着查看它们的形状时
no matter what these outer numbers are,
无论外侧的数字多大
you can always multiply two matrices
只要内侧的两个数字相同
if these numbers on the inside are the same.
都始终可以将两个矩阵相乘
And by the way, if those numbers are different,
顺便提下 如果这两个数字不同
like they were in our original example, where we would end up
例如之前的示例
with a 3 and the 2 in the middle,
中间是 3 和 2
then you just can't multiply them.
则无法相乘
It doesn't work.
行不通
Now, let's take a look at these two examples.
现在看看这两个示例
In both cases, their inner dimensions match.
两种情况下 内侧大小都匹配
So we can multiply them.
所以可以相乘
Notice how the numbers in both of these left matrices
注意 这两个示例左侧矩阵的数字
are actually the same.
是一样的
They're just arranged into a different shape, 2
只是变成了不同的形状
by 3 versus 3 by 2, and likewise for the matrices on the right.
2 x 3 与 3 x 2 右侧的矩阵也一样
But these slight changes in shape
但是这种形状的微小变化
have a big effect on the actual results
会对这些乘法的实际结果
of these multiplications.
产生很大的影响
Not only are the numbers in the answers
不仅仅答案中的数字不一样
different, the sizes of the answers are different.
而且得到矩阵的大小也不一样
We get a 2 by 2 matrix in one case, and a 3
一个是 2 x 2 的矩阵
by 3 in the other.
另一个是 3 x 3 的矩阵
This brings us to our second point
这就要提到关于矩阵乘法的
about matrix multiplication.
第二个规则
The answer matrix always has the same number
答案矩阵的行数始终与
of rows as the left matrix and the same number
左侧矩阵的行数相同
of columns as the right matrix.
列数与右侧矩阵的列数相同
Again, you can see it easily when you read out their shape
同样 当你紧挨着查看它们的形状时
side by side.
就很容易看出
This time, we're looking at these two
这次我们查看的是
numbers on the outside.
外侧的这两个数字
The first one is the number of rows for the first matrix.
第一个表示的是得到矩阵的行数
And the last one is the number of columns
最后一个表示得到矩阵的
for the second matrix.
列数
These define the shape of the answer in the same order, rows
这些数字定义了答案矩阵的形状
by columns.
即行乘以列
So multiplying this 2 by 3 matrix by this 3 by 2 matrix
所以将 2 x 3 的矩阵乘以 3 x 2 的矩阵
gives you this 2 by 2 matrix.
得出 2 x 2 的矩阵
And multiplying these matrices, that are 3 by 2 and 2 by 3,
将 3 x 2 的矩阵乘以 2 x 3 的矩阵
gives you this 3 by 3 matrix.
得出 3 x 3 的矩阵
And multiplying a 10,000 by 300 matrix by a 300 by 6,000 matrix
将 10,000 x 300 的矩阵乘以 300 x 6,000 的矩阵
would give you a 10,000 by 6,000 matrix.
得出 10,000 x 6,000 的矩阵
I want to take a look at one more example.
再看一个示例
Here, we want to multiply these two matrices.
现在我们将这两个矩阵相乘
We can see from these 3's and their shapes
从形状中的这些 3 可以看出
that it's safe to multiply them.
我们可以进行乘法运算
And these outer dimensions tell us we'll get a 2 by 2 matrix
外侧的大小告诉我们结果将是 2 x 2 的矩阵
as a result. In fact, we'll get this 2 by 2 matrix.
实际上结果是这个 2 x 2 的矩阵
Now, let's take those same two matrices,
现在再看看这两个矩阵
but swap their order in the multiplication.
但是交换下相乘顺序
When we look at their shapes in this order, we get 3 by 2 and 2
如果按这种顺序查看它们的形状
by 3.
则是 3 x 2 和 2 x 3
Those inner 2's tell us that we can safely multiply them
内侧的两个 2 告诉我们
in this order as well.
也可以按照这种顺序相乘
But the outer dimensions tell us the result will be a 3
但是外侧的大小告诉我们结果将是
by 3 matrix.
3 x 3 的矩阵
Calculating the product gives us this result.
计算出来的积是这样的结果
This brings us to our third point about matrix
这就得出了矩阵乘法的第三个规则
multiplication, order matters.
乘法顺序很重要
If you have two matrices, A and B, then the product AB
如果有两个矩阵 A 和 B 那么积 A·B
is not the same as the product BA.
与积 B·A 不相同
Standard multiplication is commutative,
标量乘法满足交换律
which means you can change the order of the items
意味着你可以更改
in the multiplication, and you'll still
乘数的顺序
get the same answer, 2 times 5 and 5 times 2 both equal 10.
结果依然相同 2 x 5 和 5 x 2 都等于 10
But as you just saw, matrix multiplication
但是正如刚才看到的 矩阵乘法
is definitely not commutative.
不满足交换率
Sometimes the sizes will only line up one way or the other.
有时候矩阵大小决定它们进行乘法的顺序
For example, a 4 by 2 matrix and 3 by 4
例如 4 x 2 矩阵和 3 x 4 矩阵
matrix can only be multiplied in one order.
只能以一种顺序相乘
This way it works, but this way it doesn't.
这样可以相乘 这样就不行
Other times, like in the previous example,
在其他情况下 例如之前的示例中
you can multiply them in either order,
两种顺序都可以相乘
but you'll get different results.
但是结果不同
And just to make sure you don't think
并且一定要明白
it's only related to the size, consider these two
不仅与大小相关
square matrices.
看看这两个方阵
Multiplying them in either order produces the same sized result.
两种顺序的积结果大小一样
But notice how the values in each of the answers
但是每个答案里的值
are different.
却不相同
This leads me to the last point I
这就得出了矩阵乘法的
want to make about matrix multiplication.
最后一个规则
It's actually something I mentioned
实际上我在之前的视频中
in the previous video.
提过
Whenever you multiply two matrices,
两个矩阵相乘
you're actually dealing with the rows of the first matrix
实际上针对的是第一个矩阵的行
and the columns of the second matrix.
与第二个矩阵的列
But now, it should be easier to see why that's important.
但是现在更容易明白为何这很重要
If you're not careful, your dot products
如果不仔细的话
might combine the wrong elements,
点积可能就是将错误的元素相结合
which would give you the wrong answer,
并得出错误的答案
even if the multiplication looks like it works.
尽管看起来你算的对的
I'll go into that some more in the next video.
我将在下个视频中详细介绍
So remember, when you build your matrices,
记住 在构建矩阵时
organize your data into rows or columns,
请将数据整理成行或列
and then be sure to line up all your math appropriately.
然后正确地使用相应的数学运算公式
By the way, I know this was a long video.
顺便提下 我知道这个视频时间很长
So I've listed out the main points
所以我列出了你需要记住的
you need to remember about matrix multiplication,
矩阵乘法知识点
and included those in the class notes below.
并放在了下面的课程注释中